Guide to the Dan & Ellen Trachtenberg papers, 1977-1989 MS 756
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Dan & Ellen Trachtenberg papers
1977-1989
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Trachtenberg, Ellen; Trachtenberg, Dan
MS 756
.25 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection contains news clippings, newsletters, event programs, photographs, and slides that document a small part of Ellen and Dan Trachtenberg's activism to improve conditions for Soviet Jews.
Biographical / Historical
Ellen Jane Fishman grew up in New Orleans, Louisiana and attended Tulane University. Daniel Stephen Trachtenberg was born and raised in Seminole, Oklahoma. The two married on March 6, 1971. They settled in Houston and began attending Congregation Beth Yeshurun over forty years ago. One of the couples many causes over the years was participating in the effort to improve the lives of jews in the Soviet Union during the 1980s.
Scope and Contents
News clippings, newsletters, event programs, photographs, and slides document a small part of Ellen and Dan Trachtenberg's activism in support of Soviet Jews and attempts to better their lives. Of particular interest are photographs taken on a trip to the Soviet Union in 1985, and news clippings of protests held in Washington D.C. in support of Soviet Jews.
Arrangement
The material in this collection has been arranged in six series as follows:
Series I: Correspondence; Series II: Event Materials; Series III: News Clippings; Series IV: Newsletters; Series V: Photographic Material; Series VI: Realia Series VII: Addenda
Conditions Governing Access
The material is open for research. Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ellen and Dan Trachtenberg donated the material in May 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
clippings (information artifacts); photographs; negatives (photographic); slides (photographs); newsletters
Places
Soviet Union
Subjects (Corporations)
Congregation Beth Yeshurun (Houston, Tex)
- Series I: Correspondence, 1986-1987
  - Correspondence from U.S.S.R., 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Event Materials, 1983-1988
  - Event programs, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Light One Candle concert, 1987-12-06 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III: News Clippings, 1983-1989
  - News Clippings, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Newsletters, 1985-1988
  - Newsletters, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series V: Photographic Materials, 1985
  - Photo album - trip to U.S.S.R., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Slides from U.S.S.R trip, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Negatives, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs U.S.S.R., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs from trip to U.S.S.R., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Realia, n.d.
  - Stainless steel bracelet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Free Soviet Jews" button, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series VII: Addenda
  - Materials from trip to U.S.S.R. (planning, logistics, travel diary), 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anatoly Sharansky bracelet, 1977 (Box 1, Envelope 1)